Inventory of the Richard Billups Papers 1705-1857
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Richard Billuups Papers, 1705-1857, 1774-1822.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 65 B49
4,308 items.
Business, military and legal papers, chiefly 1774-1822, of Richard Billups of Mathews and Gloucester Counties, Virginia.
Richard Billups.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
>Deposit: 4,006 items, 7/18/1941.
Deposit: 302 items, 4/12/1942.
Biographical/Historical Information
Richard Billups was a merchant; shipbuilder; shipowner; justice of the peace; sheriff of Mathews County, Virginia, 1792-1795; major in the Virginia militia; leader in the Methodist Episcopal Church; and member of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1807-1817, from Matthews County.
Scope and Content Information
Business, military and legal papers, chiefly 1774-1822, of Richard Billups of Mathews and Gloucester Counties, Virginia. Papers include accounts, land records, and correspondence and some concern shipbuilding. Includes minutes, 1842, of a temperance meeting and Methodist church records.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 8 Series:
1. Accounts
2. Account Books
3. Legal Papers
4. Letters
5. Military Papers
6. Society Papers
7. Printed Material
8. Oversized Material
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by date. The names mentioned with each folder are just a few of the many names which appear on the documents included within that folder.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Methodist Church--Virginia.; Temperance--History--19th century.
Geographical Names:
Mathews County (Va.)--History.; Gloucester County (Va.)- -History.
Occupations:
Shipbuilding--Virginia.
Components List
  Series 1: Accounts
- Accounts, 1757-1857. (Box 1-5)
  Including plats of land, receipts, etc.
  - Accounts in the eighteenth century, 1757-1799. (Box 1-2)
    - Accounts, 1757. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Robert Whiting, John Billups.
    - Accounts, 1761. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Thos. Flowerdewe, Benjamine Cook.
    - Accounts, 1764-1765. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Taylor, Burton, Dellahaunty, Beatley.
    - Accounts, 1766. (Box-folder 1:4)
      George Hunley, Ziperus Degges.
    - Accounts, 1767. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Jas. Davis, etc.
    - Accounts, 1768-1769. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Stubblefield, Burton, Jarvis, Lyell.
    - Accounts, 1771. (Box-folder 1:7)
      John Billups, John Steer, John Foster, Jr.
    - Accounts, 1772. (Box-folder 1:8)
      John Foster, John Billups, Geo. Foster, Wm. Armistead, etc.
    - Accounts, 1773. (Box-folder 1:9)
      John Billups, L. Smith, Wm. Reynolds, Nelson.
    - Accounts, 1774. (Box-folder 1:10)
      Billups, L. Smith, Nelson, Reynolds, Shackelford, David Jameson, Jr., Issac Foster, small account booklet.
    - Accounts, 1775. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Armistead, John Billups, Reynolds, Shackelford.
    - Accounts, 1776. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Thos. Gibbons, Thos. Flipper
    - Accounts, 1777. (Box-folder 1:13)
      John Fowler, Mathias James.
    - Accounts, 1778. (Box-folder 1:14)
      John and Richard Billups, Thos. Billups.
    - Accounts, 1779. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Billups, John Weston, Delahaunty, Taylor.
    - Accounts, 1780. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Billups, John Fowler, John Avery, Joshua Gayle, Rispess.
    - Accounts, 1781. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Richard and John Billups, Thos. Lilly.
    - Accounts, 1782. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Billups, Richard Risby.
    - Accounts, 1783. (Box-folder 1:19)
      Respess, Mathews, Foster, Pennock, Risby, Billups.
    - Accounts, 1784. (Box-folder 1:20)
      John Lilly, Billups, John Foster, Henry Forrest, etc.
    - Accounts, 1785. (Box-folder 1:21)
      John and Isaac Foster, Richard Risby, Billups, etc.
    - Accounts, 1786. (Box-folder 1:22)
      R. Risby, Estate of John Foster, Billups.
    - Accounts, 1787. (Box-folder 1:23)
      James Callis, Repass, Billups, Risby.
    - Accounts, 1788. (Box-folder 1:24)
      Estate of Wm. Lilly, Respass, Risby, Billups, etc.
    - Accounts, 1789. (Box-folder 1:25)
      Respass, Lilly, Callis, Knight, etc.
    - Accounts, 1790. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Respass, Foster, Forrest, Knight, Charlton, Jones, Tinsley, etc.
    - Accounts, 1791. (Box-folder 1:27)
      Rispass, Roberts, Foster, Mathews, etc.
    - Accounts, 1792. (Box-folder 1:28)
      Many names on accounts with Clerk or Sheriff, Mathews County.
    - Accounts, 1792. (Box-folder 1:29)
      Rispess, Risby, Anderson, Lilly, Gayle, Davis land plats.
    - Accounts, 1793 (Box-folder 2:1)
      Many names on accounts with Clerk or sheriff, Mathews County.
    - Accounts, 1793. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Lilly, Foster, Respass, Jarvis, Anderson, Dudley, Knight, etc.
    - Accounts, 1794. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Accounts, 1794. (Box-folder 2:4)
      More accounts as Folder 3; general account names as above including Rispess, Gwathmey, Dabnet. Etc.
    - Accounts, 1795. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Respass, Cooke, Tabb, many sheriff's accounts, etc.
    - Accounts, 1796. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Respass, Dixon, Foster, Anderso, Hunley, Reynolds, Callis, etc.
    - Accounts, 1797. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Repspass, Forrest, Degges, Hurst, Knight,LeRoy Cole, etc.
    - Accounts, 1798. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Respass, Eddens, Knight, Van Bibber, Dudley, etc.
    - Accounts, 1799. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Respass, Smith, Foster, Knight Schacelford, Patterson, etc.
  - Accounts in the nineteenth century, 1800-1857. (Box 3-5)
    - Accounts, 1800. (Box-folder 3:1)
      Parker, Lilly, Smith, Callis, Foster, Forrest, Respass, Knight, etc.
    - Accounts, 1801. (Box-folder 3:2)
      Smith, Knight, Respess, Gayle, David, Brounley, Saunders, etc.
    - Accounts, 1802. (Box-folder 3:3)
      Lilly Smith, Respess, Knight, Foster, Degges, Hudgin, etc.
    - Accounts, 1803. (Box-folder 3:4)
      Smith, Parrott, Mays, Knight, Respass, etc.
    - Accounts, 1804. (Box-folder 3:5)
      Jarvis, Lilly, Knight, Callis, Brown, Gayle, Eddins, etc.
    - Accounts, 1805. (Box-folder 3:6)
      Degges, Eddins, Knight, Lilly, Brown, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts, 1806. (Box-folder 3:7)
      Foster, Forrest, Eddens, Boswell, Knight, Brounley, etc.
    - Accounts, 1807. (Box-folder 3:8)
      Eddens, Lilly, Armistead, Foster, Tabb, Wjite, Burniston (?).
    - Accounts, 1807. (Box-folder 3:9)
      Accounts in connection with building of new schooner "County Norton."
    - Accounts, 1808. (Box-folder 3:10)
      Foster, Forrest, Dudley, Morgan, Burling, Brounley, etc.
    - Accounts, 1809. (Box-folder 3:11)
      Cole, Degges, Timberlake, Williams, Forest, White, Davis, Tyree, Hudgin, Tomkins, etc.
    - Accounts, 1810. (Box-folder 4:1)
      Dawson, Eddens, Bahannon, Forrest, Foster, Burneston, Burling, Mann Page, etc.
    - Accounts, 1811. (Box-folder 4:2)
      Cole, Jarvis, Forrest, Gayle, Widgeon, Lane, etc.
    - Accounts, 1812. (Box-folder 4:3)
      Respress, Foster, Hudgin, Eddens, Callis, Roberts, etc.
    - Accounts, 1813. (Box-folder 4:4)
    - Accounts, 1814. (Box-folder 4:5)
      Plat of ground; Foster, Smith, Knight, Eddens, Winder, etc.
    - Accounts, 1815. (Box-folder 4:6)
      Foster, Degges, Smith, Morgan, etc.
    - Accounts, 1816. (Box-folder 4:7)
      Cramp, Lewis, Davis, Bohannon, Stevens, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts, 1817. (Box-folder 4:8)
      Foster, Tompkins, Brounley, Hugin, Tomblin, Minter, etc.
    - Accounts, 1818. (Box-folder 4:9)
      Bramhall, Robens, Tompkins, Foster, Hayes, Eddens, etc.
    - Accounts, 1819. (Box-folder 4:10)
      Bounley, Foster, James, Ransone, Bramhall, King, etc.
    - Accounts, 1820. (Box-folder 4:11)
      Minster, Tompkins, Armistead, Diggs, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts, 1821. (Box-folder 4:12)
      March, Tompkins, Armistead, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts, 1822. (Box-folder 4:13)
      Callis, Foster, Davis, Respass, etc.
    - Accounts, 1823. (Box-folder 4:14)
      Tompkins, Winder, Wjite, James, Diggs, etc.
    - Accounts, 1824. (Box-folder 4:15)
      Forrest, Deggs, Knight, Callis, Tompkins, Edwards, etc.
    - Accounts, 1825. (Box-folder 4:16)
      Morgan, Tompkins, Davis, Diggs, etc.
    - Accounts, 1826. (Box-folder 4:17)
      Hudgin, Tompkins, Jarvis, etc.
    - Accounts, 1827. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Diggs, Tabb, Minter, Smith, Tompkins, etc.
    - Accounts, 1828. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Dunston, Stoakes, Tompkins, March, etc.
    - Accounts, 1829. (Box-folder 5:3)
      Stokes, March, Tompkins, Davis, Gambill, etc.
    - Accounts, 1830. (Box-folder 5:4)
      Foushee, Freeman, Tompkins, Crawford, Neale, etc.
    - Accounts, 1831. (Box-folder 5:5)
      March, Stoaks, Tompkins, Davis, etc.
    - Accounts, 1832. (Box-folder 5:6)
      Stoaks, Smith, Moore, Owins, Tompkins, Hudgin, etc.
    - Accounts, 1833. (Box-folder 5:7)
      Stoaks, Edwards, Minter, Kane, Walker, etc.
    - Accounts, 1834. (Box-folder 5:8)
      Stoaks, Silverthorn, Goodrich, Hodges, etc.
    - Accounts, 1835. (Box-folder 5:9)
      Stoaks, White, Diggs, armstrong, Tabb, etc.
    - Accounts, 1836. (Box-folder 5:10)
      Brounly, Richardson, Stoakes, Hall, Lane, etc.
    - Accounts, 1837. (Box-folder 5:11)
      Roy, Jones, Stoakes, Minter, Roberts, James, etc.
    - Accounts, 1838-1839. (Box-folder 5:12)
      Ransome, Stoakes, Lane, Belvin, James, etc.
    - Accounts, 1840. (Box-folder 5:13)
      Stoakes, Evans Roberts, Foster, Lumpkin, Ransone, etc.
    - Accounts, 1841. (Box-folder 5:14)
      Stoakes, Knight, Respess, Jarvis, Evans, etc.
    - Accounts, 1842. (Box-folder 5:15)
      Stoakes, Callis, Bonsal, March, etc.
    - Accounts, 1843-1844. (Box-folder 5:16)
      Brounly, Stokes, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts, 1845. (Box-folder 5:17)
      Thomas, Stoakes, Sibley, Lane, Foster, Brounly, etc.
    - Accounts, 1846. (Box-folder 5:18)
      Stoakes, Evans, etc.
    - Accounts, 1847-1848. (Box-folder 5:19)
      Stoakes, Lilly, etc.
    - Accounts, 1849-1850. (Box-folder 5:20)
      Hudgins, etc.
    - Accounts, 1851-1857. (Box-folder 5:21)
      Hudgins, Marchant, Hundley, Taylor, Foster, etc.
  - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:22-28)
    - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:22)
      Lilly, Respess, Foster, Deggs, etc.
    - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:23)
      Appleman, De la Roche, Deggs, etc.
    - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:24)
      Respess, Hunley, Forrest, Shackelford, etc.
    - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:25)
      Respess, Armistead, Knight, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:26)
      Foster, Rispess, Mathews, Ransome, Callis, Gregory.
    - Accounts, n.d. (Box-folder 5:27)
      Tabb, Lewis, Lilly, Foster, etc.
    - Accounts - Plats of land, n.d. (Box-folder 5:28)
      Plats of land. Eddins, Foster, Elliott, Booker, Ransome.
  Series 2:Account Books
- Account Books, Cash Memo, and Day Books, 1773-1839. (Box 6-7)
  - Account and Memo Book, unnamed merchant, 1773-1786. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Account book or ledger, unnamed merchant, 1777-1779. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Account book, unnamed merchant, 1785-1787. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Invoice Book, Richard Billups, 1797-1798. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Memo and pocket book - for? Billups, Kingston Parish, 1778-1799. (Box 6)
  - Account book, rum sales - Probably Richard Billups, 1785-1786. (Box 6)
  - Sheriff's ledger kept by Richard Billups, 1792-1794 (Box 6)
  - Sheriff's account book, Richard Billups, 1795-1805 (Box 6)
  - Account book of Richard Billups, 1797-1814 (Box 6)
  - Account book, Richard Billups, merchant and surveyor, 1797-1822. (Box 6)
  - Printed almanac interleaved with accounts and memos of Richard Billups, 1811-1814. (Box 6)
  - Accounts of collections and sermons, memos, unidentified clergyman, 1839-1840. (Box 6)
  - Account book, unidentified merchant, 1797-1880., 150 pages. (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Cash book, cover bears name John Billups, 1798-1801., 14 pages. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Account book with index; Richard Billups?, .1800-1801, 27 pages. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Account or day book; Richard Billups?, 1800-1801., 30 pages. (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Account or day book; Richard Billups?, 1800-1802., 45 pages. (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Account book, unidentified merchant, 1802., 10 pages. (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Accountbook, Richard Billups, 1802-1803., 14 pages. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Account book unidentified merchant, 1803., 14 pages. (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Account book, Richard Billups?, 1804-1807., 25 pages. (Box-folder 7:9)
  Series 3: Legal Papers
- Legal Papers, 1726-1855. (Box 8-9)
  - Legal Papers - deed, 1726., Poor condition. (Box-folder 8:1)
    Deed? Smither?
  - Indenture between Robert Whiting and John Hanbur, 1753. (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Legal Papers, 1770-1779. (Box-folder 8:3)
    Rum import certificate, Baltimore, 1777.
  - Legal Papers, 1780-1789. (Box-folder 8:4)
    Will of John Billups, July 20, 1785. Import certificate, Fredericksburg 1788.
  - Deed with survey, Richard Billups, 1791. (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Legal Papers, 1793. (Box-folder 8:6)
    Respess, Flitchett, Foster, Wjite.
  - Legal Papers, 1794. (Box-folder 8:7)
    Ransome, Gayle, Callis, Gregory, Davis.
  - Legal Papers, 1795. (Box-folder 8:8)
    Brown, Langley, Respess, White, Hunley, Foster.
  - Legal Papers, 1796. (Box-folder 8:9)
    Gayle, Brown.
  - Legal Papers, 1797. (Box-folder 8:10)
    Taylor, Richard Billups, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1798. (Box-folder 8:11)
    Taylor, Richard Billups, Respess.
  - Legal Papers, 1799. (Box-folder 8:12)
    Billups-Patterson, Lewis, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1800. (Box-folder 8:13)
    Billups, Shackelford
  - Legal Papers, 1801. (Box-folder 8:14)
    Hudgins, Blake, Respess, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1802-1803. (Box-folder 8:15)
    Respess, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1804. (Box-folder 8:16)
    Billups.
  - Legal Papers, 1805. (Box-folder 8:17)
    Gibbons, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1806. (Box-folder 8:18)
    Brounley, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1807. (Box-folder 8:19)
    Gibbon, etc.
  - Petition to House of Delegates, 1808. (Box-folder 8:20)
    Petition regards Richard Billups, Eddins, Gayle, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1809. (Box-folder 8:21)
    Smith, Foster, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1810-1811. (Box-folder 8:22)
    Minutes of the House of Delegates Feb. 5, 1810. Litchfield, Williams, Forrest, White, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1812-13. (Box-folder 8:23)
    Winder, Lilly, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1814. (Box-folder 8:24)
    Smith, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1815. (Box-folder 8:25)
    Degges, Brounley, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1817. (Box-folder 8:26)
    Davis, Lewis, Degges, Callis, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1818. (Box-folder 8:27)
    Hudgins, Daniel, Foster, Swann, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1819. (Box-folder 8:28)
    Lyne, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1820. (Box-folder 9:1)
    Degge, Tompkins, Forest, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1821. (Box-folder 9:2)
    Ransone, Diggs, Whting, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1822. (Box-folder 9:3)
    Lilly, Hunley, Jarvis, Booker, Smith, Degge, Gayle, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1823-1824. (Box-folder 9:4)
    Diggs, Armistead, Winder, Foster, Knight, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1825. (Box-folder 9:5)
    Bohannon, Burcher, Ransone, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1826. (Box-folder 9:6)
    Bohannon, Foster, Gayle, Ransone, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1827-1830. (Box-folder 9:7)
    Foster, Hudgins, Ransone, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1831. (Box-folder 9:8)
    Eddins, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1836-1837. (Box-folder 9:9)
    Knight, Foster, Winder, Anderson (Marriage licenses)
  - Legal Papers, 1838-1839. (Box-folder 9:10)
    Tax levy note book; Geo Paul marriage license; Hurst-Stewart marriage license.
  - Legal Papers, 1840-1849. (Box-folder 9:11)
    Diggs, Hunley, Edwards, Jarvis, Ransone, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1850-1851. (Box-folder 9:12)
    Miller, Bayly, White, Foster, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1852. (Box-folder 9:13)
    Hudgins, White, Richardson, Thomas, Williams, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1853. (Box-folder 9:14)
    Hudgins, White, Pratt, Owens, Bassett, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1854. (Box-folder 9:15)
    Edwards, Foster, Davis, Richardson, Hudgins, etc.
  - Legal Papers, 1855. (Box-folder 9:16)
    Davis, Lane, James, Hurst, Calles, etc.
  - Legal Papers, n.d. (Box-folder 9:17)
    Court docket for May term; Griffin.
  Series 4: Letters and Memos
- Letters and Memos, 1772-1847, n.d. (Box-folder 8:18-25)
  - Letters, 1772-1776. (Box-folder 9:18)
    Wilkins, Respess, Smith, etc.
  - Letters, 1790-1798. (Box-folder 9:19)
    Patterson, Tabb, Jones, etc.
  - Letters, 1801-1806. (Box-folder 9:20)
    Brown, Gibbons, Patterson, Tyree, etc.
  - Letters, 1810-1819. (Box-folder 9:21)
    Lilly, Ransone, Fowler, Muire, Jackson, etc.
  - Letters, 1820-1827. (Box-folder 9:22)
    McCandlish, Tabb, Stevens, James, Lilly, Gayle, etc.
  - Letters, 1835-1838. (Box-folder 9:23)
    Eddins, Stoaks, Dudley, etc.
  - Letters, 1841-1847. (Box-folder 9:24)
    Smith, Stoakes, March, Callis, Gayle, etc.
  - Letters, n.d. (Box-folder 9:25)
    Minter, brig construction, etc.
  Series 5: Military Papers
- Military Papers, 1797-1822, n.d. (Box-folder 9:26-28)
  - Military Papers, 1797-1808. (Box-folder 9:26)
    Gayle, Hughes, Hudgins, Van Bibber, Hurst, etc.
  - Military Papers, 1812-1813. (Box-folder 9:27)
    Lists of men, Weedon, Gayle, etc.
  - Military Papers, 1814-1822, n.d. (Box-folder 9:28)
    Nicholas, Gayle, Callis; lists of men, etc. Includes 2 items with no date.
  Series 6:Society Papers
- Society Papers, Church Meetings and School Compositions, 1811-1842, n.d (Box-folder 9:29-30)
  - Society Papers, 1811-1835. (Box-folder 9:29)
    Quarterly meeting minutes, lists of names.
  - Society Papers, 1842, n.d. (Box-folder 9:30)
    Total Abstinence Society Minutes, 1842; religious notes; composition on astronomy by Martha E. Stoakes, no date.
- Sale of Glebe Lands, 1810-1814. (Box-folder 9:31)
  Sale of the Glebe lands with regard to logs sold, work done; and a map, etc.
  Series 7: Printed Material
- Printed Material, 1811-1812, n.d. (Box-folder 9:32)
  Literary fund broadsides, Richmond 1811-1812. Clippings, no date.
  Series 8: Oversized Material
- Oversized Material, 1705-1799. (Box-folder 10:1-12)
  - Will of George Billups of Milford Haven, Gloucester County, Virginia, 6 January 1705., 2 copies. (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Will of Richard Billups of Kingston Parish, Gloucester County, Virginia, 31 January 1751. (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Will of Wilckerson Hunley of Kingston Parish, Gloucester County, Virginia, 27 February 1747. (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Court Orders, 1772-1795. (Box-folder 10:2)
  - Oversized Material, 1712, n.d. (Box-folder 10:3)
    Account of William Jarrott, Wilkerson Hunley, George Hunley, Edward Hughes, and 2 maps of Property, one dated 22 Oct. 1712.
  - Minutes of the vestry of Kingston Parish and legal papers, 16 April 1785. (Box-folder 10:4)
  - Minutes of Methodist meetings in Gloucester County, Virginia, 1806, 1813. (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Wills, 1784, 1785. (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Deeds, indentures of George Billups, John Billups, and John Mathews, n.d. (Box-folder 10:7)
  - Receipts, 1769-1774. (Box-folder 10:8)
  - Receipts, 1796-1799. (Box-folder 10:9)
  - Legal papers, n.d.. (Box-folder 10:10)
  - Papers dealing with the estate of Richard Billups and William A. Lilley, 1785. (Box-folder 10:11)
  - Papers relating to the estate of John Lilly and Zadoc Litchfield; Richard Billups, executor, n.d. (Box-folder 10:12)
  - Account book volume containing genealogical information inside the back cover, 1777-1797. (Box 10)